Guide to the Julius Silver Papers MC.165
New York University Archives
Julius Silver Papers
1945-1990
1962-1980
New York University Archives
Silver, Julius
MC.165
6 Linear Feet in 11 boxes and 1 oversize folder
Julius Silver graduated from New York University's University College of Arts and Science in 1922. After graduating from Columbia University's School of Law, Silver served as partner in a law firm and also as vice-president of the Polaroid Corporation. Throughout his life, Silver donated generously to a variety of universities and research centers. His papers primarily focus on his business and philanthropic activities, including the construction of NYU residential centers, Columbia's Silver Center of Law, Science, and Technology, and the Julius Silver Institute of Biomedical Engineering Sciences at Technion-Israel Institute of Technology.
Conditions Governing Access
Materials are open without restrictions.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Materials found in collection; there is no documentation concerning the provenance of these materials.
Arrangement
Folders are arranged by subject in five series:
I. Buildings
II. Julius Silver Institute of Bio-Medical Engineering
III. Jewish Theological Seminary of America
IV. Awards, Dedications, Photographs, and Objects
V. Newspaper Clippings and Correspondence
Biographical Note
A leading attorney, corporate executive, and philanthropist, Julius Silver (1900-2001) was born in Philadelphia, Pennsylvania, to Russian immigrants. The Silvers moved to Brooklyn, where Julius spent his childhood before receiving a scholarship to attend New York University. He graduated with a B.A. from the University College of Arts and Sciences in 1922 and was one of two members of his class elected to Phi Beta Kappa. In 1924, he graduated from Columbia School of Law with a LL.B. degree.
Silver ultimately served as a senior partner at the New York law firm Silver, Saperstein, Barnett and Solomon and as the Chairman of the Executive Committee and Vice President of the Polaroid Corporation. He was also deeply concerned with the problems and needs of higher education. He donated money to NYU to establish the Julius Silver Residence Center, the Julius Silver Scholarships for Students in the Sciences, and the Helbein Scholarships for Outstanding Student Leaders.
Silver also contributed to the development of the Albert Einstein Foundation for Higher Learning and was a primary mover in the founding of Brandeis University, the establishment of the Julius Silver Institute of Biomedical Engineering at Techion-Israel Institute of Technology, and the Julius Silver Chair in Law, Science and Technology at Columbia Law School. Silver also made a significant contribution to the New York University Faculty of Arts and Sciences upon his death, donating $150 million dollars to lure top professors to the university.
Scope and Contents
These papers primarily focus on Silver's business and philanthropic activities, including the construction of NYU residential centers, Columbia's Silver Center of Law, Science, and Technology, and the Julius Silver Institute of Biomedical Engineering Sciences at Technion-Israel Institute of Technology. The material chiefly includes correspondence regarding donations and awards, press releases, published papers and brochures, documentation related to the development of centers and institutes funded by Julius Silver, color transparencies, and miscellaneous family photographs.
Polaroid Corporation.; Biomedical engineering.; Columbia University. School of Law; Brademas, John, 1927-2016; New York University. University College of Arts and Pure Science; Jewish Theological Seminary of America
- Series I: Buildings
  - NYU Student Residence Facilities, 1963 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Minutes: Meetings of the Building and Grounds Committee of the Board of Trustees of NYU, 1965-1969 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - NYU Residence Center Copies of Julius Silver Speech, undated (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Related Materials Building of Grounds Committee, 1965-1973 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - NYU Residence Center Misc., 1963 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - NYU Residence Center Correspondence - After Dedication, 1964 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - NYU Residence Center Correspondence Prior to Dedication, 1964 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Julius Silver Residence Center Invitations, Programs, Etc., 1963 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Julius Silver NYU Residence Center Invitations, Programs, etc., 1963 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - NYU Dedication Silver Towers, 1974 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Julius Silver Reception and Dedication, 1983-1985 (Box 1, Folder 11)
- Series II: Julius Silver Institute of Bio-Medical Engineering Sciences at Technion-Israel Institute of Technology
  - Julius Silver Institute, undated (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Technion-Israel Institute of Technology Brochures, 1971 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Technion Memos and Pamphlets, 1968-1971 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Technion Pamphlets and Correspondences, 1974-1976 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Technion Bio-Medical Engineering at Technion, 1976 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Speech Notes (Technion), 1973 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Dedication Ceremonies (Technion), 1968 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - National Biomedical Engineering Center, 1966-1968 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Technion Correspondence, 1978-1985 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Technion Correspondence, 1976-1986 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Technion Correspondences and Reports, 1976-1990 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Technion Correspondences and Reports, 1976-1992 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Dedication Ceremonies of Julius Silver Institute, 1968-1976 (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Second Annual Julius Silver Symposium at Technion, 1970-1993 (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Julius Silver Symposium, 1993 (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Technion Correspondence, 1968 (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - Technion Correspondence, 1969 (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - Technion Correspondence, 1970 (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - Technion Correspondence, 1971 (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - Technion Correspondence, 1972 (Box 2, Folder 18)
  - Technion Correspondence, 1973 (Box 2, Folder 19)
  - Technion Correspondence, 1974 (Box 2, Folder 20)
  - Technion Correspondence, 1975 (Box 2, Folder 21)
  - Technion Correspondence, 1976 (Box 2, Folder 22)
  - Technion Correspondence, 1977 (Box 2, Folder 23)
  - Technion Correspondence, 1968-1970 (Box 2, Folder 24)
  - Technion Correspondence, 1978-1981 (Box 2, Folder 25)
  - Technion-Israel Institute of Technology Brochures, 1969-1970 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Technion Brochures, correspondences, and pamphlets, 1978-1994 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Description Biomedical Engineering Doctorate Program, 1971 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Technion Floor Plan, n.d. (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Julius Silver Institute floor plans, n.d. (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Julius Silver Institute Floor Plans photos, n.d. (Box 3, Folder 6)
- Series III: Jewish Theological Seminary of America
  - Correspondence of Jewish Theological Institute, 1968 (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Jewish Theological Seminary Report, 1977 (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - Jewish Theological Seminary Correspondence, 1968-1972 (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - Jewish Theological Seminary Correspondence, 1968-1975 (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - Jewish Theological Seminary of America, 1971 (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - Honorary Doctor of Humane Letters, honors causa, diploma, 1973 (Box Shared University Archives 050, Folder 6)
- Series IV: Awards, Dedications, Photographs and Objects
  Scope and Contents
  Items in this series without box and folder numbers are oversized items located in the Memorabilia Room.
  - Helbein Scholarship Award, 1982-1990 (Box 3, Folder 12)
  - Barnard College Reunion Class of 1927, 1970 (Box 3, Folder 13)
  - NYU Presidents Council Correspondence, 1965-1969 (Box 3, Folder 14)
  - Jewish Theological Seminary Award, 1966 (Box 3, Folder 15)
  - Peace In Our Time? (book), 1940 (Box 3, Folder 16)
  - Albert Einstein Award, 1989 (Box 3, Folder 17)
  - Julius Silver Institute of Bio-Medical Engineering Photo, undated (Box 3, Folder 18)
  - Photocopy of New York Times Cover December 17, 1900, undated (Box 3, Folder 19)
  - Sir Harold Acton Society Medal with program, 2002 (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Photograph of Enid Silver Winslow, undated (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - Photographs of Rosalyn Silver, undated (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - Photograph of Class of 1922 45th Reunion, 1967 (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - Framed photograph of Roslyn and Enid Silver, undated (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - Framed photograph of Enid Silver Winslow at the piano, undated (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - Framed photograph of Enid Silver Winslow, undated (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - Framed wedding photograph of Enid Silver Winslow, undated (Box 4, Folder 8)
  - Framed photograph of Enid Silver Winslow, undated (Box 4, Folder 9)
  - Framed photograph of Julius Silver, undated (Box 4, Folder 10)
  - Photographs and slides of Julius Silver, undated (Box 4, Folder 11)
  - Framed photograph of unidentified man, undated
  - Framed photo of Julius Silver Institute of Bio-Medical Engineering Sciences, Technio City, Haifa, undated
  - Framed photograph of Julius Silver, undated
  - Jewish Theological Seminary of America Honorary Doctorate, 1973
  - The Albert Einstein Award, undated (Box 11)
  - Jewish Theological Seminary certificate of gratitude and appreciation (Emes Editions Limited), 1980-12-04 (Flat-file-folder 1 Left)
  - Technion - Israel Institute of Technology certificate (signed), undated (Flat-file-folder 3 Right)
- Series V: Newspaper clippings and correspondence
  - Newspaper clippings, 1973-1976 (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - NYU Alumni newspapers, 1963 (Box 5, Folder 2)
  - Polaroid Corporation stock certificates, 1962-1969 (Box 5, Folder 3)
  - Newspaper clippings, 1967-1968 (Box 5, Folder 4)
  - Special Israel Fund materials, 1972-1975 (Box 5, Folder 5)
  - Correspondence, 1977 (Box 5, Folder 6)